# Nathan Riopelle

Human-Computer Interaction Ph.D. Student, Carnegie Mellon University

5530 5th Ave Pittsburgh, PA 15232 (571)-499-3442 ⋈ nriopell@andrew.cmu.edu

### Research Interests

I research the next generation of interactive hardware technologies to address existing limitations in performance, capability, and usability. New devices should not just fix the shortcomings reported by users of current ones but also enable previously impossible and delightful forms of interaction.

Technical Areas: Human-Computer Interaction, Smart Environments, AR/VR, Mobile Health, Ubiquitous Computing

#### Education

09/2020 - Present Carnegie Mellon University,

Pittsburgh, PA Human-Computer Interaction Institute,

Ph.D. in Human-Computer Interaction.

09/2016 - 05/2020 University of Michigan,

Ann Arbor, MI Bachelors of Science in Engineering in Computer Engineering,

GPA: 3.94/4.00.

# Professional Experience

09/2018 - 03/2020 Interactive Sensing and Computing Lab, University of Michigan, Undergrad-Ann Arbor, MI uate Researcher,

Advisor: Alanson Sample

Designed a wrist-worn device to detect different ways a user interacts with objects or surfaces and determine their activity by measuring properties of the body and the environment. Completed assembly of an embedded device integrating capacitive and electromagnetic sensors. Performed successful demos of the individual sensing components demonstrating the ability to classify user actions (capacitive) and environmental conditions (EM) using machine learning.

06/2019 - 08/2019 Microsoft Corporation, Azure Storage Media and Edge, SWE Intern,

Redmond, WA Mentor: Aniket Malatpure

Developed a root-cause analysis pipeline for Azure Stack in Python allowing for automatic filtering of potential root failures of failure during the build process staring from only a list of error events. Wrote a research paper describing the how the dependency graph algorithm I wrote could be applied to any private cloud system. Accepted for publication as first author at ISSRE 2020.

05/2018 - 08/2018 Microsoft Corporation, Azure Storage Media and Edge, SWE Intern,

Bellevue, WA Mentors: Aniket Malatpure, Suman Nath

Integrated an instrumentation tool prototyped by Microsoft Research for discovering hard-to-find fault injection and thread-safety bugs earlier in development into product code for Azure Stack. Augmented the tool to simulate cloud computing faults by performing context analysis on previous bug logs and simulating similar root causes elsewhere in the code to expose new bugs. Promoted the tool to other teams in Azure where it has already begun to enter use and find bugs.

09/2017 - 05/2018 Robert Dick Group, University of Michigan, Undergraduate Researcher,

Ann Arbor, MI Advisor: Robert Dick

Developed an embedded sensing and actuation device for aiding anesthesiologists in improving the accuracy and efficiency of epidural procedures. Aided in the process of using machine learning algorithms to correlate needle depth with sensor data to identify when the needle is approaching bone before the doctor makes contact.

05/2017 - 08/2017 The MITRE Corporation, Electronic System Dev, Embedded Software Intern, Bedford, MA Mentors: Rachel Bainbridge, Chris Niessen

> Researched electromagnetic fault attacks on cryptographic algorithms implemented on FPGAs. Programmed embedded cores in Verilog and scripts for attack testing in Python. Created an automated demo to highlight the results of the attack that educated visiting sponsors. Led a team in an embedded capture the flag competition to design, build, and defend a secure ATM banking system in C and Python and attack opposing systems with cryptanalytic techniques to capture flags. Placed in the top 5 teams.

12/2016 - 05/2017 Lab11, University of Michigan, Undergraduate Researcher,

Ann Arbor, MI Advisors: Prabal Dutta, Branden Ghena

Resolved errors in the preexisting implementation of a Bluetooth low-energy embedded audio sensor. Redesigned the device after performing power analytics to bring the project to an operational state.

06/2015 - 08/2015 U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, Laboratory for Autonomous Systems Re-Washington, D.C. search, Robotics Intern,

Mentor: Donald Sofge

Worked on a project to use bat-like echolocation via an FPGA sensor platform to identify different terrains an autonomous robot encountered. Utilized MATLAB, LabVIEW, and Python scripts to extract echoes from an ultrasonic sensor and developed a support vector machine algorithm that successfully classified four terrain types. Published as first author at the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (2018).

#### **Publications**

## Conference Papers

- C.03 V. Varga, G. Vakulya, B. Buergisser, N. Riopelle, F. Zund, R. Sumner, T. Gross, A. Sample, Real-Time Interaction Capture through Physical Contact for Mixed Reality, In Proceedings of the International Conference on Tangible, Embedded and Embodied Interaction, (TEI 2021)
- C.02 N. Riopelle, A. Malatpure, S. Ashtekar, V. Raman, Dependency Graph-based Failure Analysis for Private Clouds, *In Proceedings of the International Symposium* on Software Reliability Engineering, (ISSRE 2019)
- C.01 N. Riopelle, P. Caspers, D. Sofge, Terrain Classification for Autonomous Vehicles Using Bat-Inspired Echolocation, *In Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Neural Networks*, (IJCCN 2018)

#### Posters

P.01 N. Riopelle, A. Sample, ActiMate: A Wrist-Based, Heterogeneous Sensor Platform for Recognizing User Activities and Routines, *University of Michigan Engineering Research Symposium*, November 8, 2019

#### Awards

- 03/2020 UM EECS Department Outstanding Research Award.
- 03/2019 UM EECS Department Outstanding Achievement Award.
- 03/2019 UM EECS Scholar Award.
- 02/2019 UM Henry Ford II Prize Nominee (from Computer Engineering).
- 03/2018, 03/2019 UM James B. Angell Scholar.
  - 03/2017 UM William J. Branstrom Freshman Prize.
- 12/2016 04/2020 UM Dean's List.
- 12/2016 04/2020 UM University Honors.

#### Teaching Experience

Winter 2020 EECS 598-015 Engineering Interactive Systems, Instructional Aide.